[Music]
welcome back to reality asserts itself
on the real news network we're
continuing our series of interviews with
john keriaku the former cia officer who
spent
23 months in jail and as we record the
interview it's got about 36
37 days left under house arrest
because well really because he went on
television and said that torture was
official u.s policy he was
charged with giving a reporter the name
of a cia
officer who the reporter actually never
published and
as far as i understand it the name was
out there anyway but
they wanted to get them and we'll get in
that story more in detail further into
the series but now we're going to carry
on
we had in the last episode talked a lot
about the iraq war but a year before the
iraq war
more or less john is posted to pakistan
and
thanks for joining us good to be here
now anyone who knows the situation in
afghanistan knows
that and i don't think anybody disputes
that the pakistan
army intelligence the isi to a large
extent was some saudi
cooperation and money helped nurture and
create the taliban yes pakistani
intelligence services
created the taliban with saudi money
with saudi money
and start to spread wahhabism which is
not
the religious cultural traditions of
afghanistan
the the taliban and all the links with
al qaeda
and osama bin laden clearly the
pakistani intelligence
are not only fully aware of it the
taliban
works in collaboration with the
pakistani isi
so the osama bin laden in afghanistan is
done in some ways under the auspices of
the pakistani intelligence service
i always believe that the and i was told
that in kandahar
and there seemed to be no disputing it
so you go to pakistan in 2002 you're the
counter terrorism
chief cia opera official in pakistan
so what do you what is this relationship
with pakistan the pakistani military
intelligence is involved in creating the
taliban they've got to know about the
connections with al-qaeda and bin laden
we give them what i can't remember the
number but it's hundreds of millions of
dollars in military support
and it's it's much somewhat like the
saudi relationship but you have
clearly a dual game going with the fact
that absolutely
absolutely a dual game the the
pakistanis that great
champion of democracy and human rights
benazir bhutto
created the taliban and the original
reason for creating the taliban
was to protect pakistani truck traffic
as it drove across afghanistan
to deliver goods in iran because the
country was in chaos the country was in
utter chaos as a result of president
carter as a big neb brzezinski
and ronald reagan's policy of sucking
russia into a new vietnam they correctly
destroyed the place
that's right it was literally destroyed
so the taliban began by protecting the
trucks
then they began setting up posts in
villages along the truck routes then
they took over the villages then they
took over the regions then they took
over the states and the next thing you
know they took over the whole country
and and from what i know and i was there
and i made a film there and spoke to a
lot of afghans
in the early days it was quite popular
even amongst the secular
modern afghans in kabul because the
place was going to [__]
that's right and at least in those early
days of the taliban people weren't being
killed in shootouts in the street or or
having your relatives kidnapped and
lynched because of a property dispute
they really did bring law and order in
those early days and they did protect
pakistan's
truck traffic but then everything spun
out of control
and uh the next thing we know there's a
militant theocracy in afghanistan
i believe that even after things went
bad
in afghanistan with the taliban that
the pakistani government continued to
support them
continue to fund them and continue to
give them
safe haven when they needed it uh which
led to
no end of problems including probably
the september 11th attacks
so you're you're now head of
counterterrorism
for the cia and pakistan you're working
with pakistani authorities
and how does this work within pakistani
authorities some of them are off here
playing ftse with the al-qaeda and the
taliban and the other ones are working
with you that's a great question uh and
the answer is
is uh kind of complicated the pakistani
authorities
who were assigned to work with us almost
entirely
army officers all had been
educated in the uk trained in the uk
or the u.s solidly pro-american
and i can honestly tell you with a
completely straight face
that i never asked them for anything
that they didn't give me
anything i needed it was done and i mean
from the lowliest
private all the way up to the brigadier
general who was in charge of the program
well not everything you must have asked
them where bin laden was they didn't
with that said there were certainly
other
very powerful elements of the pakistani
uh
government specifically the pakistani
military
that were solidly pro-taliban
in many cases pro-al-qaeda and
did not just nothing to help us but
actively tried to
to stop us from making inroads against
al qaeda
even in the abu zabeta operation we
never told the pakistanis who we were
going after
we called him mr fish because we had
told them that he was a big fish
so the night that we hit okay give some
context we haven't told that story yet
sure uh just after my arrival in
pakistan
we got word from headquarters that abu
zubato was somewhere in the country and
at the time
we thought abu zubaydah was the number
three in al-qaeda that turned out to not
be true
not only was he not the number three
khalid sheikh muhammad was the number
three
but abu zubaydah had never actually
joined al-qaeda
he created and ran al-qaeda's two
training camps
but he never pledged fealty to osama bin
laden he was an independent
operator so we were afraid
that the people that we were dealing
with on a daily basis
would tell somebody in their
organization who the target was
and that word would get out and abu
zubair would be tipped off
so we never told them until we actually
had him in custody
who it was we had been looking for
where'd the intelligence come from that
he was number three
oh you know he get bits and pieces from
various human sources you get
liaison sources reporting to our liaison
officers overseas
you might get some intercepts press
reporting you put everything together
and you try to come up with this
structure for al-qaeda
and the best information we had in 2002
was that he was number three don't
forget in
in february of 2002 we didn't know who
khalid sheikh muhammad was
we we had no idea not only that
that he was a major player in al qaeda
but that he had masterminded the 9 11
attacks that's how bad the intelligence
was back then
okay so you grab this guy now
you're in on organizing the mission to
grab this guy
how did that go we had we had never hit
more than two sites simultaneously
uh before in pakistan we would my first
day on the job i
went into the senior cia officer's
office and i said what exactly do you
want me to do here
and he said i want you to come up with a
modus operandi for taking down a
terrorist safe house
we've not done that yet i said okay so i
remember sitting at my desk
with a legal pad and a pen and and
thinking
well if i was going to take down a
terrorist safe house how would i start
well i would do it at 2 a.m because they
would most likely be asleep by 2 a.m so
i wrote 0-200 at the top of the paper
and then i just tried to come up with
this step-by-step plan
of how i wanted to do it so finally i
went to him and i said i think i've come
up with a plan i'm ready to give it a
try
and he said well we got this little bit
of information that there's this house
here's the address
and there might be an al-qaeda guy in it
i said all right i'll get a group of
guys together
and uh we're going to hit it tonight at
2 and you know wish me luck and you've
never done this
i had never done this before and i
understand this i i would have imagined
the cia had these specialists take down
houses specialists and
in they fly in jack bauer shows up that
all came later
because of september 11th but before i
mean it was
it was sad sacks like me it's cia's been
doing ops for
since they founded the thing but not
like this though this was different
so uh i came up with a plan i got a
couple of the guys together
we called our pakistani uh counterparts
and i said listen why don't we meet up
at 12
i'm gonna brief you on this operation
that i want us to do tonight
so we did and um
i planned it so that we were about a
block away from the house
at 1 55 a.m and then at 1 57 we were
going to get out of the car
and then we were going to walk to the
house and then right at o200 and we
synchronized our watches
we're going to use a battering ram to
break down the door of the house
pakistani is always going first it's
their country
we're going to grab the guy and take him
into custody so
that's what we did o200 we broke down
the door with the battering ram
and we caught this 19 year old tunisian
kid
who had just escaped across the border
from afghanistan
and found refuge in this house so i said
hey
success well let's try it again in a
couple of nights
and the second time we did it we caught
an egyptian who had been a member of
egyptian islamic jihad
he was actually wanted in egypt had been
charged with crimes there and had
escaped to afghanistan
and i thought okay well this is pretty
good once or twice we did two in a night
we would set up two separate teams and
do it
and almost every time we did this we
would catch somebody
and they were almost exclusively
low-level nobodies
usually teenagers they would just start
to cry
they wouldn't resist in any way you know
what happened with them uh we would send
them
usually back to afghanistan or in some
cases to guantanamo
remember the whole purpose of guantanamo
in those early days
was just to have some place to put them
until we could figure out where to put
them on trial
if they should be tried in the u.s or
flown back to their home countries to be
tried there
guantanamo was never ever supposed to be
a permanent uh
some of the people you picked up and
sent to guantanamo
you didn't know they'd actually done
anything other than they're in this
house correct
correct but my position back then was if
you're in
arab in pakistan with no money
no job no passport and no plausible
explanation for what you're doing there
and how you got there you're al-qaeda
and you're going to go to guantanamo
until we can figure out what we what we
are going to do with you
there were so many people we had to go
after
there was just no time to to really
go into things with them to decide yes
this
is really who they are this is why
they're here and another thing is
many of them most of them had been
briefed in advance
on what to do and what to say if you're
captured
so everybody told us the same exact
story
and the story was that they had gone to
pakistan
to learn arabic they were going to take
arabic classes
which is odd because nobody speaks
arabic in pakistan
they speak or these were mostly afghans
they were all arabs
but how could they go to learn arabic
precisely
so they flew to karachi
and they were so happy to have arrived
safely in karachi that they decided
to take a taxi to the grand mosque to
thank god for their safe delivery well
there is no grand mosque in karachi the
grand mosque is an islamabad
and they accidentally dogged on it left
their passports in the taxi
and that's why they have no passport and
so
they didn't know where to stay where to
live so they went to the local arab
coffee shop
there is no arab coffee shop in any of
these places
and they met some arabs there from their
own country and
the arabs said oh not to worry i'll put
you in this house
and you wait there until i can get the
embassy to replace your
uh your passport okay so no matter what
country they came from
they all told exactly the same story
so these are just you think young naive
recruits that didn't know
they were nobodies so then you go and
you go after what you think is the
number three
it was more complicated than that we we
got this message from headquarters
saying that
abu zubaydah was in pakistan and we had
to catch him but pakistan is the size of
texas
and it has the population of california
so to say just go catch him
it meant nothing to me so we flew an
analyst in from headquarters what was
then called a
targeting analyst somebody who isn't
thinking the big thoughts to write an
article in the president's daily brief
about you know
a country's next election but somebody
who's focused on pouring through raw
data
to try to locate someone who we have as
a target
and it took him about i'm going to say
two or three weeks
and finally he came to me and said i've
narrowed it down but only to 14
possible locations well we had never hit
more than two spots before in a single
night
so the prospect of hitting 14
simultaneously was daunting
i cabled headquarters and i said
i'm going to need help so
you you go after the guy who's number
three
and you get the guy and this begins a
chain of events
which actually winds you up in jail
really and you can date that chain
probably from around here
yes because some of your colleagues go
off
to question this guy and what happens
abu zubaydah was very severely wounded
when we captured him a pakistani
policeman shot him three times with an
ak-47
and he nearly died in fact the doctor at
the emergency room where we took him
that night told me
that he had never seen wounds so severe
where the patient lived
so we flew abu zubaydah to a nearby
military base and i sat with him for
almost 48 hours actually it was more
than 40 i had eight hours
i thought it was 48 hours and then in
discovery in my case i learned it was 56
hours
so i just sat at the foot of his bed
just quickly when
sorry john says my case he means when
the cia charged him
that's right and they were going through
all the back and forth of discoveries
that eventually led to
his conviction and and go back to
earlier and you'll find out he was in
jail for 23 months
and is now under house arrest and we're
going to tell this whole story
in the next segment or two so i sat with
him for 56 hours
he was in a coma for most of that he
drifted out of it a couple of times at
one point he asked me to smother him
with a pillow
uh he asked me for a glass of red wine
which i thought was just a delusion
but then later on the next day
he was a little more aware of what had
happened
and we talked about the 9 11 attacks
briefly
we talked about christianity and islam
he told me that he enjoyed writing
poetry he cried he said he would never
know the touch of a woman
he would never know the joy of
fatherhood and i
urged him repeatedly to cooperate and
he said no that he he wasn't going to
cooperate
he told me at one point you seem like a
nice guy
but you're the enemy and i'll never
cooperate with the enemy
so did it did he say why you're the
enemy
well i was an american it was it was as
simple as
that he did say that that he didn't want
to attack the united states on september
11th
that that was bin laden's decision he
wanted to attack israel
um but bin laden overruled him and said
no that they were attacking the united
states
but he never there was no ambiguity or
qualification from him that
911 was bin laden oh no no no
none at all 9 11 was bin laden most
definitely
so um his wounds like i say were so
severe he really needed to be treated
uh formally treated not just patched up
so the cia
sent a private jet with
a trauma surgeon from johns hopkins
university medical center
uh they flew to the military base and uh
three fbi agents and i loaded him onto
uh
onto a gurney and carried him up onto
the plane
we laid him across the luggage rack at
the back and
he took off he went to a so-called
secret location
and i never saw him again now you heard
about the interrogation what did you
hear yes
i heard when i got back to headquarters
i heard that
he had been uncooperative that he had
been subjected to waterboarding one time
and that he had cracked and after he
cracked
he gave us actionable intelligence that
saved american lives
that turned out to be a complete lie
he had not been waterboarded one time he
had been waterboarded
83 times in fact he was cooperative
when he was being interviewed by the fbi
we know from the fbi agent who was
interviewing him that he was cooperative
and this fbi agent ali soufan
had made real inroads in this
relationship with abu
beta what happened then was
the president ordered the fbi out the
cia
in and the cia began torturing him
using several different methods and
culminating in waterboarding
how do you know is the president that
ordered it well
that's what came out over the course of
the investigation later on
that these these uh
tactics had all been approved by the
president and that the white house was
unhappy with the pace of
the interrogations they wanted
information more quickly
see bin laden said right after september
11th that he was planning
another attack that would dwarf what
happened on september 11th
so many cia officers were convinced that
abu zubaydah had that information
and they were determined to get it out
of him that's why they got rough so
quickly
okay there's a lot of discussion
in the media and there was in political
circles and so on about
torture and the waterboarding and
the pakistani connection with the
taliban and all the rest
but what do you think of the bigger
picture the overall policy
of allying with essentially what
more or less is a military close to has
been a military dictatorship in pakistan
and when it's not a straightforward
dictatorship it's behind the scenes
military rule just beneath the sort of
political
structure aligning with warlords in
afghanistan
allying with uh you know a dictatorial
monarchy in saudi arabia
qatar go on and on and on that in that
in order to maintain america as the
hegemon
in the region we have to
we we said earlier you know do bad
things supposedly for good reasons
ally with the the worst kind of forces
you could possibly dredge up
yes i think as a country we're going to
have to make a decision
at some point and that decision is going
to have to be
whether we are going to be this beacon
of human rights
that we'd like to think we are this
shining city on a hill
that everybody looks up to where
everybody wants to move
or are we going to be the biggest
toughest bully on the block
because we can't be both at the same
time you know i was i i happened to be
on the state department's website the
other day
and i clicked on the link for the bureau
of democracy human rights and labor
and right at the top of their website
they have a link to the universal
declaration on human rights
and article 5 of that declaration says
that no person shall be subjected to
torture
or to humiliating treatment okay this is
a joke
congress mandates the state department
every single year with producing a human
rights report
on every single country with which we
have diplomatic relations
i was the embassy human rights officer
for two years
in bahrain when i was living there and i
can tell you
that when you go in to
to a host government's foreign ministry
and you dress them down for
disrespecting human rights
but then you have a cia officer going to
see his counterpart in the afternoon
and telling him telling the the foreign
intelligence
counterpart we want you to take this
prisoner and we want you to really lean
on him but just be sure to give us a
transcript of what he says
you completely undercut your entire
policy
so while we have these these laws
that are supposed to protect human
rights
and supposed to mandate the protection
of human rights overseas
it's really little more than a bad joke
because we don't respect human rights
i mean we we had under george w bush
our own justice department doing
backflips
to try to figure out how to legally
justify torture
and they contorted themselves in such a
way that they did
endorse torture and we go through
life saying okay well then if the
justice department said it's right
then it must be right so we can go ahead
and torture
it makes no sense it's been non-stop
since world war ii
it's been non-stop since world war ii
you know i'll tell you another thing
in the course of my my research since
i've left the agency i found a picture
that ran on the front page of the
washington post in 1968
and it was a picture of an american
soldier waterboarding a north vietnamese
prisoner
when that picture was published the
pentagon
began an investigation they
court-martialed the soldier
they charged him with torture they
convicted him and they jailed him
so why was torture wrong in 1968
but then it's right in 2002 and it's
right in 2015
and nobody's prosecuted for committing
torture it's it's
it's the ultimate in hypocrisy to me all
right thanks for joining us
we're going to continue our series of
interviews with john kiriakou on reality
asserts itself
on the real news network
[Music]
you